Prologue

David Garrick, Esq.

Enter Mr. Woodward, dressed in black, and holding a handkerchief to his eyes.

Excuse me, sirs, I pray—I can’t yet speak—
Excuse me, sirs, I pray—I can’t yet speak—
I’m crying now—and have been all the week.
“ ’Tis not alone this mourning suit,” good masters:
“I’ve that within”—for which there are no plasters!
Pray, would you know the reason why I’m crying?
The Comic Muse, long sick, is now a-dying!
And if she goes, my tears will never stop;
For as a player, I can’t squeeze out one drop:
I am undone, that’s all—shall lose my bread—
I’d rather, but that’s nothing—lose my head.
When the sweet maid is laid upon the bier,
Shuter and I shall be chief mourners here.
To her a mawkish drab of spurious breed,
Who deals in sentimentals, will succeed!
Poor Ned and I are dead to all intents;
We can as soon speak Greek as sentiments!
Both nervous grown, to keep our spirits up.
We now and then take down a hearty cup.
What shall we do? If Comedy forsake us,
They’ll turn us out, and no one else will take us.
But why can’t I be moral?—Let me try—
My heart thus pressing—fixed my face and eye—
With a sententious look, that nothing means,
(Faces are blocks in sentimental scenes)
Thus I begin: “All is not gold that glitters,
“Pleasure seems sweet, but proves a glass of bitters.
“When Ignorance enters, Folly is at hand:
“Learning is better far than house and land.
“Let not your virtue trip; who trips may stumble,
“And virtue is not virtue, if she tumble.”

I give it up—morals won’t do for me;
To make you laugh, I must play tragedy.
One hope remains—hearing the maid was ill,
A Doctor comes this night to show his skill.
To cheer her heart, and give your muscles motion,
He, in Five Draughts prepar’d, presents a potion:
A kind of magic charm—for be assur’d,
If you will swallow it, the maid is cur’d:
But desperate the Doctor, and her case is,
If you reject the dose, and make wry faces!
This truth he boasts, will boast it while he lives,
No poisonous drugs are mixed in what he gives.
Should he succeed, you’ll give him his degree;
If not, within he will receive no fee!
The College you, must his pretensions back,
Pronounce him Regular, or dub him Quack.

Act II

Scene. An old-fashioned house.

Enter Hardcastle, followed by three or four awkward Servants.
Hardcastle | Well, I hope you are perfect in the table exercise I have been teaching you these three days. You all know your posts and your places, and can show that you have been used to good company, without ever stirring from home.
Omnes | Ay, ay.
Hardcastle | When company comes you are not to pop out and stare, and then run in again, like frightened rabbits in a warren.
Omnes | No, no.
Hardcastle | You, Diggory, whom I have taken from the barn, are to make a show at the side-table; and you, Roger, whom I have advanced from the plough, are to place yourself behind my chair. But you’re not to stand so, with your hands in your pockets. Take your hands from your pockets, Roger; and from your head, you blockhead you. See how Diggory carries his hands. They’re a little too stiff, indeed, but that’s no great matter.
Diggory | Ay, mind how I hold them. I learned to hold my hands this way when I was upon drill for the militia. And so being upon drill—
Hardcastle | You must not be so talkative, Diggory. You must be all attention to the guests. You must hear us talk, and not think of talking; you must see us drink, and not think of drinking; you must see us eat, and not think of eating.
Diggory | By the laws, your worship, that’s parfectly unpossible. Whenever Diggory sees yeating going forward, ecod, he’s always wishing for a mouthful himself.
Hardcastle | Blockhead! Is not a bellyful in the kitchen as good as a bellyful in the parlour? Stay your stomach with that reflection.
Diggory | Ecod, I thank your worship, I’ll make a shift to stay my stomach with a slice of cold beef in the pantry.
Hardcastle | Diggory, you are too talkative.—Then, if I happen to say a good thing, or tell a good story at table, you must not all burst out a-laughing, as if you made part of the company.
Diggory | Then, ecod, your worship must not tell the story of Ould Grouse in the gun room: I can’t help laughing at that—he! he! he!—for the soul of me. We have laughed at that these twenty years—ha! ha! ha!
Hardcastle | Ha! ha! ha! The story is a good one. Well, honest Diggory, you may laugh at that; but still remember to be attentive. Suppose one of the company should call for a glass of wine, how will you behave? A glass of wine, sir, if you please—To Diggory. Eh, why don’t you move?
Diggory | Ecod, your worship, I never have courage till I see the eatables and drinkables brought upo’ the table, and then I’m as bauld as a lion.
Hardcastle | What, will nobody move?
First Servant | I’m not to leave this pleace.
Second Servant | I’m sure it’s no pleace of mine.
Third Servant | Nor mine, for sartain.
Diggory | Wauns, and I’m sure it canna be mine.
Hardcastle | You numskulls! and so while, like your betters, you are quarrelling for places, the guests must be starved. Oh, you dunces! I find I must begin all over again—But don’t I hear a coach drive into the yard? To your posts, you blockheads. I’ll go in the meantime and give my old friend’s son a hearty reception at the gate.
Exit Hardcastle.
Diggory | By the elevens, my pleace is gone quite out of my head.
Roger | I know that my pleace is to be everywhere.
First Servant | Where the devil is mine?
Second Servant | My pleace is to be nowhere at all; and so I’ze go about my business.
Exeunt Servants, running about as if frightened, different ways.
Enter Servant with candles, showing in Marlow and Hastings.
Servant | Welcome, gentlemen, very welcome! This way.
Hastings | After the disappointments of the day, welcome once more, Charles, to the comforts of a clean room and a good fire. Upon my word, a very well-looking house; antique but creditable.
Marlow | The usual fate of a large mansion. Having first ruined the master by good housekeeping, it at last comes to levy contributions as an inn.
Hastings | As you say, we passengers are to be taxed to pay all these fineries. I have often seen a good sideboard, or a marble chimney piece, though not actually put in the bill, inflame a reckoning confoundedly.
Marlow | Travellers, George, must pay in all places: the only difference is, that in good inns you pay dearly for luxuries; in bad inns you are fleeced and starved.
Hastings | You have lived very much among them. In truth, I have been often surprised, that you who have seen so much of the world, with your natural good sense, and your many opportunities, could never yet acquire a requisite share of assurance.
Marlow | The Englishman’s malady. But tell me, George, where could I have learned that assurance you talk of? My life has been chiefly spent in a college or an inn, in seclusion from that lovely part of the creation that chiefly teach men confidence. I don’t know that I was ever familiarly acquainted with a single modest woman, except my mother. But among females of another class, you know—
Hastings | Ay, among them you are impudent enough of all conscience.
Marlow | They are of us, you know.
Hastings | But in the company of women of reputation I never saw such an idiot, such a trembler; you look for all the world as if you wanted an opportunity of stealing out of the room.
Marlow | Why, man, that’s because I do want to steal out of the room. Faith, I have often formed a resolution to break the ice, and rattle away at any rate. But I don’t know how, a single glance from a pair of fine eyes has totally overset my resolution. An impudent fellow may counterfeit modesty; but I’ll be hanged if a modest man can ever counterfeit impudence.
Hastings | If you could but say half the fine things to them that I have heard you lavish upon the barmaid of an inn, or even a college bed-maker—
Marlow | Why, George, I can’t say fine things to them; they freeze, they petrify me. They may talk of a comet, or a burning mountain, or some such bagatelle; but, to me, a modest woman, drest out in all her finery, is the most tremendous object of the whole creation.
Hastings | Ha! ha! ha! At this rate, man, how can you ever expect to marry?
Marlow | Never; unless, as among kings and princes, my bride were to be courted by proxy. If, indeed, like an Eastern bridegroom, one were to be introduced to a wife he never saw before, it might be endured. But to go through all the terrors of a formal courtship, together with the episode of aunts, grandmothers, and cousins, and at last to blurt out the broad staring question of “Madam, will you marry me?” No, no, that’s a strain much above me, I assure you.
Hastings | I pity you. But how do you intend behaving to the lady you are come down to visit at the request of your father?
Marlow | As I behave to all other ladies. Bow very low, answer yes or no to all her demands. But for the rest, I don’t think I shall venture to look in her face till I see my father’s again.
Hastings | I’m surprised that one who is so warm a friend can be so cool a lover.
Marlow | To be explicit, my dear Hastings, my chief inducement down was to be instrumental in forwarding your happiness, not my own. Miss Neville loves you, the family don’t know you; as my friend you are sure of a reception, and let honour do the rest.
Hastings | My dear Marlow! But I’ll suppress the emotion. Were I a wretch, meanly seeking to carry off a fortune, you should be the last man in the world I would apply to for assistance. But Miss Neville’s person is all I ask, and that is mine, both from her deceased father’s consent, and her own inclination.
Marlow | Happy man! you have talents and art to captivate any woman. I’m doomed to adore the sex, and yet to converse with the only part of it I despise. This stammer in my address, and this awkward prepossessing visage of mine, can never permit me to soar above the reach of a milliner’s ’prentice, or one of the Duchesses of Drury Lane. Pshaw! this fellow here to interrupt us.
Enter Hardcastle.
Hardcastle | Gentlemen, once more you are heartily welcome. Which is Mr. Marlow? Sir, you are heartily welcome. It’s not my way, you see, to receive my friends with my back to the fire. I like give them a hearty reception in the old style at my gate. I like to see their horses and trunks taken care of.
Marlow | Aside. He has got our names from the servants already. To him. We approve your caution and hospitality, sir. To Hastings. I have been thinking, George, of changing our travelling dresses in the morning. I am grown confoundedly ashamed of mine.
Hardcastle | I beg, Mr. Marlow, you’ll use no ceremony in this house.
Hastings | I fancy, Charles, you’re right: the first blow is half the battle. I intend opening the campaign with the white and gold.
Hardcastle | Mr. Marlow—Mr. Hastings—gentlemen—pray be under no constraint in this house. This is Liberty Hall, gentlemen. You may do just as you please here.
Marlow | Yet, George, if we open the campaign too fiercely at first, we may want ammunition before it is over. I think to reserve the embroidery to secure a retreat.
Hardcastle | Your talking of a retreat, Mr. Marlow, puts me in mind of the Duke of Marlborough, when we went to besiege Denain. He first summoned the garrison—
Marlow | Don’t you think the ventre d’or waistcoat will do with the plain brown?
Hardcastle | He first summoned the garrison, which might consist of about five thousand men—
Hastings | I think not: brown and yellow mix but very poorly.
Hardcastle | I say, gentlemen, as I was telling you, be summoned the garrison, which might consist of about five thousand men—
Marlow | The girls like finery.
Hardcastle | Which might consist of about five thousand men, well appointed with stores, ammunition, and other implements of war. “Now,” says the Duke of Marlborough to George Brooks, that stood next to him—you must have heard of George Brooks—“I’ll pawn my dukedom,” says he, “but I take that garrison without spilling a drop of blood.” So—
Marlow | What, my good friend, if you gave us a glass of punch in the meantime; it would help us to carry on the siege with vigour.
Hardcastle | Punch, sir! Aside. This is the most unaccountable kind of modesty I ever met with.
Marlow | Yes, sir, punch! A glass of warm punch, after our journey, will be comfortable. This is Liberty Hall, you know.
Hardcastle | Here’s a cup, sir.
Marlow | Aside. So this fellow, in his Liberty Hall, will only let us have just what he pleases.
Hardcastle | Taking the cup. I hope you’ll find it to your mind. I have prepared it with my own hands, and I believe you’ll own the ingredients are tolerable. Will you be so good as to pledge me, sir? Here, Mr. Marlow, here is to our better acquaintance. Drinks.
Marlow | Aside. A very impudent fellow this! but he’s a character, and I’ll humour him a little. Sir, my service to you. Drinks.
Hastings | Aside. I see this fellow wants to give us his company, and forgets that he’s an innkeeper, before he has learned to be a gentleman.
Marlow | From the excellence of your cup, my old friend, I suppose you have a good deal of business in this part of the country. Warm work, now and then, at elections, I suppose.
Hardcastle | No, sir, I have long given that work over. Since our betters have hit upon the expedient of electing each other, there is no business “for us that sell ale.”
Hastings | So, then, you have no turn for politics, I find.
Hardcastle | Not in the least. There was a time, indeed, I fretted myself about the mistakes of government, like other people; but finding myself every day grow more angry, and the government growing no better, I left it to mend itself. Since that, I no more trouble my head about Hyder Ally, or Ally Cawn, than about Ally Croker. Sir, my service to you.
Hastings | So that with eating above stairs, and drinking below, with receiving your friends within, and amusing them without, you lead a good pleasant bustling life of it.
Hardcastle | I do stir about a great deal, that’s certain. Half the differences of the parish are adjusted in this very parlour.
Marlow | After drinking. And you have an argument in your cup, old gentleman, better than any in Westminster Hall.
Hardcastle | Ay, young gentleman, that, and a little philosophy.
Marlow | Aside. Well, this is the first time I ever heard of an innkeeper’s philosophy.
Hastings | So then, like an experienced general, you attack them on every quarter. If you find their reason manageable, you attack it with your philosophy; if you find they have no reason, you attack them with this. Here’s your health, my philosopher. Drinks.
Hardcastle | Good, very good, thank you; ha! ha! Your generalship puts me in mind of Prince Eugene, when he fought the Turks at the battle of Belgrade. You shall hear.
Marlow | Instead of the battle of Belgrade, I believe it’s almost time to talk about supper. What has your philosophy got in the house for supper?
Hardcastle | For supper, sir! Aside. Was ever such a request to a man in his own house?
Marlow | Yes, sir, supper, sir; I begin to feel an appetite. I shall make devilish work tonight in the larder, I promise you.
Hardcastle | Aside. Such a brazen dog sure never my eyes beheld. To him. Why, really, sir, as for supper I can’t well tell. My Dorothy and the cook-maid settle these things between them. I leave these kind of things entirely to them.
Marlow | You do, do you?
Hardcastle | Entirely. By the by, I believe they are in actual consultation upon what’s for supper this moment in the kitchen.
Marlow | Then I beg they’ll admit me as one of their privy council. It’s a way I have got. When I travel, I always choose to regulate my own supper. Let the cook be called. No offence I hope, sir.
Hardcastle | O no, sir, none in the least; yet I don’t know how; our Bridget, the cook-maid, is not very communicative upon these occasions. Should we send for her, she might scold us all out of the house.
Hastings | Let’s see your list of the larder then. I ask it as a favour. I always match my appetite to my bill of fare.
Marlow | To Hardcastle, who looks at them with surprise. Sir, he’s very right, and it’s my way too.
Hardcastle | Sir, you have a right to command here. Here, Roger, bring us the bill of fare for tonight’s supper: I believe it’s drawn out—Your manner, Mr. Hastings, puts me in mind of my uncle, Colonel Wallop. It was a saying of his, that no man was sure of his supper till he had eaten it.
Hastings | Aside. All upon the high rope! His uncle a colonel! we shall soon hear of his mother being a justice of the peace. But let’s hear the bill of fare.
Marlow | Perusing. What’s here? For the first course; for the second course; for the dessert. The devil, sir, do you think we have brought down a whole Joiners’ Company, or the corporation of Bedford, to eat up such a supper? Two or three little things, clean and comfortable, will do.
Hastings | But let’s hear it.
Marlow | Reading. “For the first course, at the top, a pig, and prune sauce.”
Hastings | Damn your pig, I say.
Marlow | And damn your prune sauce, say I.
Hardcastle | And yet, gentlemen, to men that are hungry, pig with prune sauce is very good eating.
Marlow | “At the bottom, a calf’s tongue and brains.”
Hastings | Let your brains be knocked out, my good sir, I don’t like them.
Marlow | Or you may clap them on a plate by themselves. I do.
Hardcastle | Aside. Their impudence confounds me. To them. Gentlemen, you are my guests, make what alterations you please. Is there anything else you wish to retrench or alter, gentlemen?
Marlow | “Item: a pork pie, a boiled rabbit and sausages, a Florentine, a shaking pudding, and a dish of tiff—taff—taffety cream!”
Hastings | Confound your made dishes; I shall be as much at a loss in this house as at a green and yellow dinner at the French ambassador’s table. I’m for plain eating.
Hardcastle | I’m sorry, gentlemen, that I have nothing you like, but if there be anything you have a particular fancy to—
Marlow | Why, really, sir, your bill of fare is so exquisite, that any one part of it is full as good as another. Send us what you please. So much for supper. And now to see that our beds are aired, and properly taken care of.
Hardcastle | I entreat you’ll leave that to me. You shall not stir a step.
Marlow | Leave that to you! I protest, sir, you must excuse me, I always look to these things myself.
Hardcastle | I must insist, sir, you’ll make yourself easy on that head.
Marlow | You see I’m resolved on it. Aside. A very troublesome fellow this, as I ever met with.
Hardcastle | Well, sir, I’m resolved at least to attend you. Aside. This may be modern modesty, but I never saw anything look so like old-fashioned impudence.
Exeunt Marlow and Hardcastle.
Hastings | Alone. So I find this fellow’s civilities begin to grow troublesome. But who can be angry at those assiduities which are meant to please him? Ha! what do I see? Miss Neville, by all that’s happy!
Enter Miss Neville.
Miss Neville | My dear Hastings! To what unexpected good fortune, to what accident, am I to ascribe this happy meeting?
Hastings | Rather let me ask the same question, as I could never have hoped to meet my dearest Constance at an inn.
Miss Neville | An inn! sure you mistake: my aunt, my guardian, lives here. What could induce you to think this house an inn?
Hastings | My friend, Mr. Marlow, with whom I came down, and I, have been sent here as to an inn, I assure you. A young fellow, whom we accidentally met at a house hard by, directed us hither.
Miss Neville | Certainly it must be one of my hopeful cousin’s tricks, of whom you have heard me talk so often; ha! ha! ha!
Hastings | He whom your aunt intends for you? he of whom I have such just apprehensions?
Miss Neville | You have nothing to fear from him, I assure you. You’d adore him, if you knew how heartily he despises me. My aunt knows it too, and has undertaken to court me for him, and actually begins to think she has made a conquest.
Hastings | Thou dear dissembler! You must know, my Constance, I have just seized this happy opportunity of my friend’s visit here to get admittance into the family. The horses that carried us down are now fatigued with their journey, but they’ll soon be refreshed; and then, if my dearest girl will trust in her faithful Hastings, we shall soon be landed in France, where even among slaves the laws of marriage are respected.
Miss Neville | I have often told you, that though ready to obey you, I yet should leave my little fortune behind with reluctance. The greatest part of it was left me by my uncle, the India director, and chiefly consists in jewels. I have been for some time persuading my aunt to let me wear them. I fancy I’m very near succeeding. The instant they are put into my possession, you shall find me ready to make them and myself yours.
Hastings | Perish the baubles! Your person is all I desire. In the meantime, my friend Marlow must not be let into his mistake. I know the strange reserve of his temper is such, that if abruptly informed of it, he would instantly quit the house before our plan was ripe for execution.
Miss Neville | But how shall we keep him in the deception? Miss Hardcastle is just returned from walking; what if we still continue to deceive him?—This, this way—They confer.
Enter Marlow.
Marlow | The assiduities of these good people tease me beyond bearing. My host seems to think it ill manners to leave me alone, and so he claps not only himself, but his old-fashioned wife, on my back. They talk of coming to sup with us too; and then, I suppose, we are to run the gantlet through all the rest of the family.—What have we got here?
Hastings | My dear Charles! Let me congratulate you!—The most fortunate accident!—Who do you think is just alighted?
Marlow | Cannot guess.
Hastings | Our mistresses, boy, Miss Hardcastle and Miss Neville. Give me leave to introduce Miss Constance Neville to your acquaintance. Happening to dine in the neighbourhood, they called on their return to take fresh horses here. Miss Hardcastle has just stepped into the next room, and will be back in an instant. Wasn’t it lucky? eh!
Marlow | Aside. I have been mortified enough of all conscience, and here comes something to complete my embarrassment.
Hastings | Well, but wasn’t it the most fortunate thing in the world?
Marlow | Oh! yes. Very fortunate—a most joyful encounter—But our dresses, George, you know are in disorder—What if we should postpone the happiness till tomorrow?—Tomorrow at her own house—It will be every bit as convenient—and rather more respectful—Tomorrow let it be. Offering to go.
Miss Neville | By no means, sir. Your ceremony will displease her. The disorder of your dress will show the ardour of your impatience. Besides, she knows you are in the house, and will permit you to see her.
Marlow | Oh, the devil! how shall I support it? Hem! hem! Hastings, you must not go. You are to assist me, you know. I shall be confoundedly ridiculous. Yet, hang it! I’ll take courage. Hem!
Hastings | Pshaw, man! it’s but the first plunge, and all’s over. She’s but a woman, you know.
Marlow | And, of all women, she that I dread most to encounter.
Enter Miss Hardcastle, as returned from walking, a bonnet, etc.
Hastings | Introducing them. Miss Hardcastle, Mr. Marlow. I’m proud of bringing two persons of such merit together, that only want to know, to esteem each other.
Miss Hardcastle | Aside. Now for meeting my modest gentleman with a demure face, and quite in his own manner. After a pause, in which he appears very uneasy and disconcerted. I’m glad of your safe arrival, sir. I’m told you had some accidents by the way.
Marlow | Only a few, madam. Yes, we had some. Yes, madam, a good many accidents, but should be sorry—madam—or rather glad of any accidents—that are so agreeably concluded. Hem!
Hastings | To him. You never spoke better in your whole life. Keep it up, and I’ll insure you the victory.
Miss Hardcastle | I’m afraid you flatter, sir. You that have seen so much of the finest company, can find little entertainment in an obscure corner of the country.
Marlow | Gathering courage. I have lived, indeed, in the world, madam; but I have kept very little company. I have been but an observer upon life, madam, while others were enjoying it.
Miss Neville | But that, I am told, is the way to enjoy it at last.
Hastings | To him. Cicero never spoke better. Once more, and you are confirmed in assurance forever.
Marlow | To him. Hem! Stand by me, then, and when I’m down, throw in a word or two, to set me up again.
Miss Hardcastle | An observer, like you, upon life were, I fear, disagreeably employed, since you must have had much more to censure than to approve.
Marlow | Pardon me, madam. I was always willing to be amused. The folly of most people is rather an object of mirth than uneasiness.
Hastings | To him. Bravo, bravo. Never spoke so well in your whole life.—Well, Miss Hardcastle, I see that you and Mr. Marlow are going to be very good company. I believe our being here will but embarrass the interview.
Marlow | Not in the least, Mr. Hastings. We like your company of all things. To him. Zounds, George, sure you won’t go? How can you leave us?
Hastings | Our presence will but spoil conversation, so we’ll retire to the next room. To him. You don’t consider, man, that we are to manage a little tête-à-tête of our own.
Exeunt Hastings with Miss Neville.
Miss Hardcastle | After a pause. But you have not been wholly an observer, I presume, sir: the ladies, I should hope, have employed some part of your addresses.
Marlow | Relapsing into timidity. Pardon me, madam, I—I—I—as yet have studied—only—to—deserve them.
Miss Hardcastle | And that, some say, is the very worst way to obtain them.
Marlow | Perhaps so, madam. But I love to converse only with the more grave and sensible part of the sex. But I’m afraid I grow tiresome.
Miss Hardcastle | Not at all, sir; there is nothing I like so much as grave conversation myself; I could hear it forever. Indeed, I have often been surprised how a man of sentiment could ever admire those light airy pleasures, where nothing reaches the heart.
Marlow | It’s—a disease—of the mind, madam. In the variety of tastes there must be some who, wanting a relish—for—um—a—um—
Miss Hardcastle | I understand you, sir. There must be some, who, wanting a relish for refined pleasures, pretend to despise what they are incapable of tasting.
Marlow | My meaning, madam, but infinitely better expressed. And I can’t help observing—a—
Miss Hardcastle | Aside. Who could ever suppose this fellow impudent upon some occasions? To him. You were going to observe, sir—
Marlow | I was observing, madam—I protest, madam, I forget what I was going to observe.
Miss Hardcastle | Aside. I vow and so do I. To him. You were observing, sir, that in this age of hypocrisy—something about hypocrisy, sir.
Marlow | Yes, madam. In this age of hypocrisy there are few who upon strict inquiry do not—a—a—a—
Miss Hardcastle | I understand you perfectly, sir.
Marlow | Aside. Egad! and that’s more than I do myself.
Miss Hardcastle | You mean that in this hypocritical age there are few that do not condemn in public what they practise in private, and think they pay every debt to virtue when they praise it.
Marlow | True, madam; those who have most virtue in their mouths, have least of it in their bosoms. But I’m sure I tire you, madam.
Miss Hardcastle | Not in the least, sir; there’s something so agreeable and spirited in your manner, such life and force—pray, sir, go on.
Marlow | Yes, madam. I was saying—that there are some occasions—when a total want of courage, madam, destroys all the—and puts us—upon a—a—a—
Miss Hardcastle | I agree with you entirely; a want of courage upon some occasions assumes the appearance of ignorance, and betrays us when we most want to excel. I beg you’ll proceed.
Marlow | Yes, madam. Morally speaking, madam—But I see Miss Neville expecting us in the next room. I would not intrude for the world.
Miss Hardcastle | I protest, sir, I never was more agreeably entertained in all my life. Pray go on.
Marlow | Yes, madam, I was—But she beckons us to join her. Madam, shall I do myself the honour to attend you?
Miss Hardcastle | Well, then, I’ll follow.
Marlow | Aside. This pretty smooth dialogue has done for me.
Exit.
Miss Hardcastle | Alone. Ha! ha! ha! Was there ever such a sober, sentimental interview? I’m certain he scarce looked in my face the whole time. Yet the fellow, but for his unaccountable bashfulness, is pretty well too. He has good sense, but then so buried in his fears, that it fatigues one more than ignorance. If I could teach him a little confidence, it would be doing somebody that I know of a piece of service. But who is that somebody?—That, faith, is a question I can scarce answer.
Exit.
Enter Tony and Miss Neville, followed by Mrs. Hardcastle and Hastings.
Tony | What do you follow me for, cousin Con? I wonder you’re not ashamed to be so very engaging.
Miss Neville | I hope, cousin, one may speak to one’s own relations, and not be to blame.
Tony | Ay, but I know what sort of a relation you want to make me, though; but it won’t do. I tell you, cousin Con, it won’t do; so I beg you’ll keep your distance, I want no nearer relationship. She follows, coquetting him to the back scene.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Well! I vow, Mr. Hastings, you are very entertaining. There’s nothing in the world I love to talk of so much as London, and the fashions, though I was never there myself.
Hastings | Never there! You amaze me! From your air and manner, I concluded you had been bred all your life either at Ranelagh, St. James’s, or Tower Wharf.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Oh, sir, you’re only pleased to say so. We country persons can have no manner at all. I’m in love with the town, and that serves to raise me above some of our neighbouring rustics; but who can have a manner, that has never seen the Pantheon, the Grotto Gardens, the Borough, and such places where the nobility chiefly resort? All I can do is to enjoy London at secondhand. I take care to know every tête-à-tête from the Scandalous Magazine, and have all the fashions, as they come out, in a letter from the two Miss Rickets of Crooked Lane. Pray, how do you like this head, Mr. Hastings?
Hastings | Extremely elegant and dégagée, upon my word, madam. Your friseur is a Frenchman, I suppose?
Mrs. Hardcastle | I protest, I dressed it myself from a print in the Ladies’ Memorandum Book for the last year.
Hastings | Indeed! Such a head in a side box at the playhouse would draw as many gazers as my Lady Mayoress at a city ball.
Mrs. Hardcastle | I vow, since inoculation began, there is no such thing to be seen as a plain woman; so one must dress a little particular, or one may escape in the crowd.
Hastings | But that can never be your case, madam, in any dress. Bowing.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Yet, what signifies my dressing when I have such a piece of antiquity by my side as Mr. Hardcastle: all I can say will never argue down a single button from his clothes. I have often wanted him to throw off his great flaxen wig, and where he was bald, to plaster it over, like my Lord Pately, with powder.
Hastings | You are right, madam; for, as among the ladies there are none ugly, so among the men there are none old.
Mrs. Hardcastle | But what do you think his answer was? Why, with his usual Gothic vivacity, he said I only wanted him to throw off his wig, to convert it into a tête for my own wearing.
Hastings | Intolerable! At your age you may wear what you please, and it must become you.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Pray, Mr. Hastings, what do you take to be the most fashionable age about town?
Hastings | Some time ago, forty was all the mode; but I’m told the ladies intend to bring up fifty for the ensuing winter.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Seriously. Then I shall be too young for the fashion.
Hastings | No lady begins now to put on jewels till she’s past forty. For instance, Miss there, in a polite circle, would be considered as a child, as a mere maker of samplers.
Mrs. Hardcastle | And yet Mistress Niece thinks herself as much a woman, and is as fond of jewels, as the oldest of us all.
Hastings | Your niece, is she? And that young gentleman, a brother of yours, I should presume?
Mrs. Hardcastle | My son, sir. They are contracted to each other. Observe their little sports. They fall in and out ten times a day, as if they were man and wife already. To them. Well, Tony, child, what soft things are you saying to your cousin Constance this evening?
Tony | I have been saying no soft things; but that it’s very hard to be followed about so. Ecod! I’ve not a place in the house now that’s left to myself, but the stable.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Never mind him, Con, my dear. He’s in another story behind your back.
Miss Neville | There’s something generous in my cousin’s manner. He falls out before faces to be forgiven in private.
Tony | That’s a damned confounded—crack.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Ah! he’s a sly one. Don’t you think they are like each other about the mouth, Mr. Hastings? The Blenkinsop mouth to a T. They’re of a size too. Back to back, my pretties, that Mr. Hastings may see you. Come, Tony.
Tony | You had as good not make me, I tell you. Measuring.
Miss Neville | O lud! he has almost cracked my head.
Mrs. Hardcastle | O, the monster! For shame, Tony. You a man, and behave so!
Tony | If I’m a man, let me have my fortin. Ecod! I’ll not be made a fool of no longer.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Is this, ungrateful boy, all that I’m to get for the pains I have taken in your education? I that have rocked you in your cradle, and fed that pretty mouth with a spoon! Did not I work that waistcoat to make you genteel? Did not I prescribe for you every day, and weep while the receipt was operating?
Tony | Ecod! you had reason to weep, for you have been dosing me ever since I was born. I have gone through every receipt in the Complete Huswife ten times over; and you have thoughts of coursing me through Quincy next spring. But, ecod! I tell you, I’ll not be made a fool of no longer.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Wasn’t it all for your good, viper? Wasn’t it all for your good?
Tony | I wish you’d let me and my good alone, then. Snubbing this way when I’m in spirits. If I’m to have any good, let it come of itself; not to keep dinging it, dinging it into one so.
Mrs. Hardcastle | That’s false; I never see you when you’re in spirits. No, Tony, you then go to the alehouse or kennel. I’m never to be delighted with your agreeable wild notes, unfeeling monster!
Tony | Ecod! mamma, your own notes are the wildest of the two.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Was ever the like? But I see he wants to break my heart, I see he does.
Hastings | Dear madam, permit me to lecture the young gentleman a little. I’m certain I can persuade him to his duty.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Well, I must retire. Come, Constance, my love. You see, Mr. Hastings, the wretchedness of my situation. Was ever poor woman so plagued with a dear sweet, pretty, provoking, undutiful boy?
Exeunt Mrs. Hardcastle and Miss Neville.
Tony | Singing. “There was a young man riding by, and fain would have his will. Rang do didlo dee.”—Don’t mind her. Let her cry. It’s the comfort of her heart. I have seen her and sister cry over a book for an hour together; and they said they liked the book the better the more it made them cry.
Hastings | Then you’re no friend to the ladies, I find, my pretty young gentleman?
Tony | That’s as I find ’um.
Hastings | Not to her of your mother’s choosing, I dare answer? And yet she appears to me a pretty well-tempered girl.
Tony | That’s because you don’t know her as well as I. Ecod! I know every inch about her; and there’s not a more bitter cantankerous toad in all Christendom.
Hastings | Aside. Pretty encouragement this for a lover!
Tony | I have seen her since the height of that. She has as many tricks as a hare in a thicket, or a colt the first day’s breaking.
Hastings | To me she appears sensible and silent.
Tony | Ay, before company. But when she’s with her playmate, she’s as loud as a hog in a gate.
Hastings | But there is a meek modesty about her that charms me.
Tony | Yes, but curb her never so little, she kicks up, and you’re flung in a ditch.
Hastings | Well, but you must allow her a little beauty.—Yes, you must allow her some beauty.
Tony | Bandbox! She’s all a made-up thing, mun. Ah! could you but see Bet Bouncer of these parts, you might then talk of beauty. Ecod, she has two eyes as black as sloes, and cheeks as broad and red as a pulpit cushion. She’d make two of she.
Hastings | Well, what say you to a friend that would take this bitter bargain off your hands?
Tony | Anon!
Hastings | Would you thank him that would take Miss Neville, and leave you to happiness and your dear Betsy?
Tony | Ay; but where is there such a friend, for who would take her?
Hastings | I am he. If you but assist me, I’ll engage to whip her off to France, and you shall never hear more of her.
Tony | Assist you! Ecod I will, to the last drop of my blood. I’ll clap a pair of horses to your chaise that shall trundle you off in a twinkling, and may he get you a part of her fortin beside, in jewels, that you little dream of.
Hastings | My dear Squire, this looks like a lad of spirit.
Tony | Come along then and you shall see more of my spirit before you have done with me. Singing.

We are the boys
That fears no noise
Where the thundering cannons roar.

Exeunt.

Act IV

Enter Hastings and Miss Neville.
Hastings | You surprise me; Sir Charles Marlow expected here this night! Where have you had your information?
Miss Neville | You may depend upon it. I just saw his letter to Mr. Hardcastle, in which he tells him he intends setting out a few hours after his son.
Hastings | Then, my Constance, all must be completed before he arrives. He knows me; and should he find me here, would discover my name, and perhaps my designs, to the rest of the family.
Miss Neville | The jewels, I hope, are safe?
Hastings | Yes, yes, I have sent them to Marlow, who keeps the keys of our baggage. In the meantime, I’ll go to prepare matters for our elopement. I have had the ’squire’s promise of a fresh pair of horses; and if I should not see him again, will write him further directions. Exit.
Miss Neville | Well! success attend you. In the meantime I’ll go and amuse my aunt with the old pretence of a violent passion for my cousin. Exit.
Enter Marlow, followed by a Servant.
Marlow | I wonder what Hastings could mean by sending me so valuable a thing as a casket to keep for him, when he knows the only place I have is the seat of a post-coach at an inn-door. Have you deposited the casket with the landlady, as I ordered you? Have you put it into her own hands?
Servant | Yes, your honour.
Marlow | She said she’d keep it safe, did she?
Servant | Yes, she said she’d keep it safe enough; she asked me how I came by it; and she said she had a great mind to make me give an account of myself. Exit Servant.
Marlow | Ha! ha! ha! They’re safe, however. What an unaccountable set of beings have we got amongst! This little barmaid though runs in my head most strangely, and drives out the absurdities of all the rest of the family. She’s mine, she must be mine, or I’m greatly mistaken.
Enter Hastings.
Hastings | Bless me! I quite forgot to tell her that I intended to prepare at the bottom of the garden. Marlow here, and in spirits too!
Marlow | Give me joy, George! Crown me, shadow me with laurels! Well, George, after all, we modest fellows don’t want for success among the women.
Hastings | Some women, you mean. But what success has your honour’s modesty been crowned with now, that it grows so insolent upon us?
Marlow | Didn’t you see the tempting, brisk, lovely little thing, that runs about the house with a bunch of keys to its girdle?
Hastings | Well, and what then?
Marlow | She’s mine, you rogue you. Such fire, such motion, such eyes, such lips; but, egad! she would not let me kiss them though.
Hastings | But are you so sure, so very sure of her?
Marlow | Why, man, she talked of showing me her work above stairs, and I am to improve the pattern.
Hastings | But how can you, Charles, go about to rob a woman of her honour?
Marlow | Pshaw! pshaw! We all know the honour of the barmaid of an inn. I don’t intend to rob her, take my word for it; there’s nothing in this house I shan’t honestly pay for.
Hastings | I believe the girl has virtue.
Marlow | And if she has, I should be the last man in the world that would attempt to corrupt it.
Hastings | You have taken care, I hope, of the casket I sent you to lock up? Is it in safety?
Marlow | Yes, yes. It’s safe enough. I have taken care of it. But how could you think the seat of a post-coach at an inn-door a place of safety? Ah! numskull! I have taken better precautions for you than you did for yourself—I have—
Hastings | What?
Marlow | I have sent it to the landlady to keep for you.
Hastings | To the landlady!
Marlow | The landlady.
Hastings | You did?
Marlow | I did. She’s to be answerable for its forthcoming, you know.
Hastings | Yes, she’ll bring it forth with a witness.
Marlow | Wasn’t I right? I believe you’ll allow that I acted prudently upon this occasion.
Hastings | Aside. He must not see my uneasiness.
Marlow | You seem a little disconcerted though, methinks. Sure nothing has happened?
Hastings | No, nothing. Never was in better spirits in all my life. And so you left it with the landlady, who, no doubt, very readily undertook the charge.
Marlow | Rather too readily. For she not only kept the casket, but, through her great precaution, was going to keep the messenger too. Ha! ha! ha!
Hastings | He! he! he! They’re safe, however.
Marlow | As a guinea in a miser’s purse.
Hastings | Aside. So now all hopes of fortune are at an end, and we must set off without it. To him. Well, Charles, I’ll leave you to your meditations on the pretty barmaid, and, he! he! he! may you be as successful for yourself, as you have been for me! Exit.
Marlow | Thank ye, George: I ask no more. Ha! ha! ha!
Enter Hardcastle.
Hardcastle | I no longer know my own house. It’s turned all topsy-turvy. His servants have got drunk already. I’ll bear it no longer; and yet, from my respect for his father, I’ll be calm. To him. Mr. Marlow, your servant. I’m your very humble servant. Bowing low.
Marlow | Sir, your humble servant. Aside. What’s to be the wonder now?
Hardcastle | I believe, sir, you must be sensible, sir, that no man alive ought to be more welcome than your father’s son, sir. I hope you think so?
Marlow | I do from my soul, sir. I don’t want much entreaty. I generally make my father’s son welcome wherever he goes.
Hardcastle | I believe you do, from my soul, sir. But though I say nothing to your own conduct, that of your servants is insufferable. Their manner of drinking is setting a very bad example in this house, I assure you.
Marlow | I protest, my very good sir, that is no fault of mine. If they don’t drink as they ought, they are to blame. I ordered them not to spare the cellar. I did, I assure you. To the side scene. Here, let one of my servants come up. To him. My positive directions were, that as I did not drink myself, they should make up for my deficiencies below.
Hardcastle | Then they had your orders for what they do? I’m satisfied!
Marlow | They had, I assure you. You shall hear from one of themselves.
Enter Servant, drunk.
Marlow | You, Jeremy! Come forward, sirrah! What were my orders? Were you not told to drink freely, and call for what you thought fit, for the good of the house?
Hardcastle | Aside. I begin to lose my patience.
Jeremy | Please your honour, liberty and Fleet-street forever! Though I’m but a servant, I’m as good as another man. I’ll drink for no man before supper, sir, damme! Good liquor will sit upon a good supper, but a good supper will not sit upon—hiccup—on my conscience, sir.
Marlow | You see, my old friend, the fellow is as drunk as he can possibly be. I don’t know what you’d have more, unless you’d have the poor devil soused in a beer-barrel.
Hardcastle | Zounds! he’ll drive me distracted, if I contain myself any longer. Mr. Marlow—Sir; I have submitted to your insolence for more than four hours, and I see no likelihood of its coming to an end. I’m now resolved to be master here, sir; and I desire that you and your drunken pack may leave my house directly.
Marlow | Leave your house!⸺Sure you jest, my good friend! What? when I’m doing what I can to please you.
Hardcastle | I tell you, sir, you don’t please me; so I desire you’ll leave my house.
Marlow | Sure you cannot be serious? At this time o’ night, and such a night? You only mean to banter me.
Hardcastle | I tell you, sir, I’m serious! and now that my passions are roused, I say this house is mine, sir; this house is mine, and I command you to leave it directly.
Marlow | Ha! ha! ha! A puddle in a storm. I shan’t stir a step, I assure you. In a serious tone. This your house, fellow! It’s my house. This is my house. Mine, while I choose to stay. What right have you to bid me leave this house, sir? I never met with such impudence, curse me; never in my whole life before.
Hardcastle | Nor I, confound me if ever I did. To come to my house, to call for what he likes, to turn me out of my own chair, to insult the family, to order his servants to get drunk, and then to tell me, “This house is mine, sir.” By all that’s impudent, it makes me laugh. Ha! ha! ha! Pray, sir, Bantering. as you take the house, what think you of taking the rest of the furniture? There’s a pair of silver candlesticks, and there’s a fire-screen, and here’s a pair of brazen-nosed bellows; perhaps you may take a fancy to them?
Marlow | Bring me your bill, sir; bring me your bill, and let’s make no more words about it.
Hardcastle | There are a set of prints, too. What think you of the Rake’s Progress, for your own apartment?
Marlow | Bring me your bill, I say; and I’ll leave you and your infernal house directly.
Hardcastle | Then there’s a mahogany table that you may see your own face in.
Marlow | My bill, I say.
Hardcastle | I had forgot the great chair for your own particular slumbers, after a hearty meal.
Marlow | Zounds! bring me my bill, I say, and let’s hear no more on’t.
Hardcastle | Young man, young man, from your father’s letter to me, I was taught to expect a well-bred modest man as a visitor here, but now I find him no better than a coxcomb and a bully; but he will be down here presently, and shall hear more of it. Exit.
Marlow | How’s this? Sure I have not mistaken the house. Everything looks like an inn. The servants cry, coming; the attendance is awkward; the barmaid, too, to attend us. But she’s here, and will further inform me. Whither so fast, child? A word with you.
Enter Miss Hardcastle.
Miss Hardcastle | Let it be short, then. I’m in a hurry. Aside. I believe he begins to find out his mistake. But it’s too soon quite to undeceive him.
Marlow | Pray, child, answer me one question. What are you, and what may your business in this house be?
Miss Hardcastle | A relation of the family, sir.
Marlow | What, a poor relation.
Miss Hardcastle | Yes, sir. A poor relation, appointed to keep the keys, and to see that the guests want nothing in my power to give them.
Marlow | That is, you act as the barmaid of this inn.
Miss Hardcastle | Inn! O law—what brought that in your head? One of the best families in the country keep an inn—Ha! ha! ha! old Mr. Hardcastle’s house an inn!
Marlow | Mr. Hardcastle’s house! Is this Mr. Hardcastle’s house, child?
Miss Hardcastle | Ay, sure! Whose else should it be?
Marlow | So then, all’s out, and I have been damnably imposed on. O, confound my stupid head, I shall be laughed at over the whole town. I shall be stuck up in caricatura in all the print-shops. The Dullissimo Maccaroni. To mistake this house of all others for an inn, and my father’s old friend for an innkeeper! What a swaggering puppy must he take me for! What a silly puppy do I find myself! There again, may I be hanged, my dear, but I mistook you for the barmaid.
Miss Hardcastle | Dear me! dear me! I’m sure there’s nothing in my behaviour to put me on a level with one of that stamp.
Marlow | Nothing, my dear, nothing. But I was in for a list of blunders, and could not help making you a subscriber. My stupidity saw everything the wrong way. I mistook your assiduity for assurance, and your simplicity for allurement. But it’s over. This house I no more show my face in.
Miss Hardcastle | I hope, sir, I have done nothing to disoblige you. I’m sure I should be sorry to affront any gentleman who has been so polite, and said so many civil things to me. I’m sure I should be sorry Pretending to cry. if he left the family upon my account. I’m sure I should be sorry if people said anything amiss, since I have no fortune but my character.
Marlow | Aside. By Heaven! she weeps. This is the first mark of tenderness I ever had from a modest woman, and it touches me. To her. Excuse me, my lovely girl; you are the only part of the family I leave with reluctance. But to be plain with you, the difference of our birth, fortune, and education, makes an honourable connection impossible; and I can never harbour a thought of seducing simplicity that trusted in my honour, of bringing ruin upon one whose only fault was being too lovely.
Miss Hardcastle | Aside. Generous man! I now begin to admire him. To him. But I am sure my family is as good as Miss Hardcastle’s; and though I’m poor, that’s no great misfortune to a contented mind; and, until this moment, I never thought that it was bad to want fortune.
Marlow | And why now, my pretty simplicity?
Miss Hardcastle | Because it puts me at a distance from one that, if I had a thousand pounds, I would give it all to.
Marlow | Aside. This simplicity bewitches me, so that if I stay, I’m undone. I must make one bold effort, and leave her. To her. Your partiality in my favour, my dear, touches me most sensibly: and were I to live for myself alone, I could easily fix my choice. But I owe too much to the opinion of the world, too much to the authority of a father; so that—I can scarcely speak it—it affects me. Farewell. Exit.
Miss Hardcastle | I never knew half his merit till now. He shall not go, if I have power or art to detain him. I’ll still preserve the character in which I stooped to conquer; but will undeceive my papa, who perhaps may laugh him out of his resolution. Exit.
Enter Tony and Miss Neville.
Tony | Ay, you may steal for yourselves the next time. I have done my duty. She has got the jewels again, that’s a sure thing; but she believes it was all a mistake of the servants.
Miss Neville | But, my dear cousin, sure you won’t forsake us in this distress? If she in the least suspects that I am going off, I shall certainly be locked up, or sent to my aunt Pedigree’s, which is ten times worse.
Tony | To be sure, aunts of all kinds are damned bad things. But what can I do? I have got you a pair of horses that will fly like Whistle-jacket; and I’m sure you can’t say but I have courted you nicely before her face. Here she comes, we must court a bit or two more, for fear she should suspect us. They retire, and seem to fondle.
Enter Mrs. Hardcastle.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Well, I was greatly fluttered, to be sure. But my son tells me it was all a mistake of the servants. I shan’t be easy, however, till they are fairly married, and then let her keep her own fortune. But what do I see? fondling together, as I’m alive. I never saw Tony so sprightly before. Ah! have I caught you, my pretty doves? What, billing, exchanging stolen glances and broken murmurs? Ah!
Tony | As for murmurs, mother, we grumble a little now and then, to be sure. But there’s no love lost between us.
Mrs. Hardcastle | A mere sprinkling, Tony, upon the flame, only to make it burn brighter.
Miss Neville | Cousin Tony promises to give us more of his company at home. Indeed, he shan’t leave us any more. It won’t leave us, cousin Tony, will it?
Tony | O! it’s a pretty creature. No, I’d sooner leave my horse in a pound, than leave you when you smile upon one so. Your laugh makes you so becoming.
Miss Neville | Agreeable cousin! Who can help admiring that natural humour, that pleasant, broad, red, thoughtless Patting his cheek.—ah! it’s a bold face.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Pretty innocence!
Tony | I’m sure I always loved cousin Con.’s hazle eyes, and her pretty long fingers, that she twists this way and that over the haspicholls, like a parcel of bobbins.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Ah! he would charm the bird from the tree. I was never so happy before. My boy takes after his father, poor Mr. Lumpkin, exactly. The jewels, my dear Con., shall be yours incontinently. You shall have them. Isn’t he a sweet boy, my dear? You shall be married tomorrow, and we’ll put off the rest of his education, like Dr. Drowsy’s sermons, to a fitter opportunity.
Enter Diggory.
Diggory | Where’s the ’squire? I have got a letter for your worship.
Tony | Give it to my mamma. She reads all my letters first.
Diggory | I had orders to deliver it into your own hands.
Tony | Who does it come from?
Diggory | Your worship mun ask that o’ the letter itself.
Tony | I could wish to know though. Turning the letter, and gazing on it.
Miss Neville | Aside. Undone! undone! A letter to him from Hastings. I know the hand. If my aunt sees it, we are ruined forever. I’ll keep her employed a little if I can. To Mrs. Hardcastle. But I have not told you, madam, of my cousin’s smart answer just now to Mr. Marlow. We so laughed.—You must know, madam.—This way a little, for he must not hear us. They confer.
Tony | Still gazing. A damned cramp piece of penmanship, as ever I saw in my life. I can read your print hand very well. But here are such handles, and shanks, and dashes, that one can scarce tell the head from the tail.—“To Anthony Lumpkin, Esquire.” It’s very odd, I can read the outside of my letters, where my own name is, well enough; but when I come to open it, it’s all—buzz. That’s hard, very hard; for the inside of the letter is always the cream of the correspondence.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Ha! ha! ha! Very well, very well. And so my son was too hard for the philosopher.
Miss Neville | Yes, madam; but you must hear the rest, madam. A little more this way, or he may hear us. You’ll hear how he puzzled him again.
Mrs. Hardcastle | He seems strangely puzzled now himself, methinks.
Tony | Still gazing. A damned up and down hand, as if it was disguised in liquor.—Reading. Dear Sir,—ay, that’s that. Then there’s an M, and a T, and an S, but whether the next be an izzard, or an R, confound me, I cannot tell.
Mrs. Hardcastle | What’s that, my dear? Can I give you any assistance?
Miss Neville | Pray, aunt, let me read it. Nobody reads a cramp hand better than I. Twitching the letter from him. Do you know who it is from?
Tony | Can’t tell, except from Dick Ginger, the feeder.
Miss Neville | Ay, so it is. Pretending to read. Dear ’Squire, hoping that you’re in health, as I am at this present. The gentlemen of the Shake-bag club has cut the gentlemen of Goose-green quite out of feather. The odds—um—odd battle—um—long fighting—um—here, here, it’s all about cocks and fighting; it’s of no consequence; here, put it up, put it up. Thrusting the crumpled letter upon him.
Tony | But I tell you, miss, it’s of all the consequence in the world. I would not lose the rest of it for a guinea. Here, mother, do you make it out. Of no consequence! Giving Mrs. Hardcastle the letter.
Mrs. Hardcastle | How’s this?—Reads. “Dear ’Squire, I’m now waiting for Miss Neville, with a post-chaise and pair, at the bottom of the garden, but I find my horses yet unable to perform the journey. I expect you’ll assist us with a pair of fresh horses, as you promised. Dispatch is necessary, as the hag (ay, the hag), your mother, will otherwise suspect us! Yours, Hastings.” Grant me patience. I shall run distracted! My rage chokes me.
Miss Neville | I hope, madam, you’ll suspend your resentment for a few moments, and not impute to me any impertinence, or sinister design, that belongs to another.
Mrs. Hardcastle | Curtseying very low. Fine spoken, madam, you are most miraculously polite and engaging, and quite the very pink of courtesy and circumspection, madam. Changing her tone. And you, you great ill-fashioned oaf, with scarce sense enough to keep your mouth shut: were you, too, joined against me? But I’ll defeat all your plots in a moment. As for you, madam, since you have got a pair of fresh horses ready, it would be cruel to disappoint them. So, if you please, instead of running away with your spark, prepare, this very moment, to run off with me. Your old aunt Pedigree will keep you secure, I’ll warrant me. You too, sir, may mount your horse, and guard us upon the way. Here, Thomas, Roger, Diggory! I’ll show you, that I wish you better than you do yourselves. Exit.
Miss Neville | So now I’m completely ruined.
Tony | Ay, that’s a sure thing.
Miss Neville | What better could be expected from being connected with such a stupid fool,—and after all the nods and signs I made him?
Tony | By the laws, miss, it was your own cleverness, and not my stupidity, that did your business. You were so nice and so busy with your Shake-bags and Goose-greens, that I thought you could never be making believe.
Enter Hastings.
Hastings | So, sir, I find by my servant, that you have shown my letter, and betrayed us. Was this well done, young gentleman?
Tony | Here’s another. Ask miss there, who betrayed you. Ecod, it was her doing, not mine.
Enter Marlow.
Marlow | So I have been finely used here among you. Rendered contemptible, driven into ill manners, despised, insulted, laughed at.
Tony | Here’s another. We shall have old Bedlam broke loose presently.
Miss Neville | And there, sir, is the gentleman to whom we all owe every obligation.
Marlow | What can I say to him, a mere boy, an idiot, whose ignorance and age are a protection?
Hastings | A poor contemptible booby, that would but disgrace correction.
Miss Neville | Yet with cunning and malice enough to make himself merry with all our embarrassments.
Hastings | An insensible cub.
Marlow | Replete with tricks and mischief.
Tony | Baw! damme, but I’ll fight you both, one after the other—with baskets.
Marlow | As for him, he’s below resentment. But your conduct, Mr. Hastings, requires an explanation. You knew of my mistakes, yet would not undeceive me.
Hastings | Tortured as I am with my own disappointments, is this a time for explanations? It is not friendly, Mr. Marlow.
Marlow | But, sir—
Miss Neville | Mr. Marlow, we never kept on your mistake till it was too late to undeceive you.
Enter Servant.
Servant | My mistress desires you’ll get ready immediately, madam. The horses are putting to. Your hat and things are in the next room. We are to go thirty miles before morning. Exit Servant.
Miss Neville | Well, well: I’ll come presently.
Marlow | To Hastings. Was it well done, sir, to assist in rendering me ridiculous? To hang me out for the scorn of all my acquaintance? Depend upon it, sir, I shall expect an explanation.
Hastings | Was it well done, sir, if you’re upon that subject, to deliver what I entrusted to yourself, to the care of another sir?
Miss Neville | Mr. Hastings! Mr. Marlow! Why will you increase my distress by this groundless dispute? I implore, I entreat you—
Enter Servant.
Servant | Your cloak, madam. My mistress is impatient. Exit Servant.
Miss Neville | I come. Pray be pacified. If I leave you thus, I shall die with apprehension.
Enter Servant.
Servant | Your fan, muff, and gloves, madam. The horses are waiting.
Miss Neville | O, Mr. Marlow! if you knew what a scene of constraint and ill-nature lies before me, I’m sure it would convert your resentment into pity.
Marlow | I’m so distracted with a variety of passions, that I don’t know what I do. Forgive me, madam. George, forgive me. You know my hasty temper, and should not exasperate it.
Hastings | The torture of my situation is my only excuse.
Miss Neville | Well, my dear Hastings, if you have that esteem for me that I think, that I am sure you have, your constancy for three years will but increase the happiness of our future connection. If—
Mrs. Hardcastle | Within. Miss Neville. Constance, why Constance, I say.
Miss Neville | I’m coming. Well, constancy, remember, constancy is the word. Exit.
Hastings | My heart! how can I support this? To be so near happiness, and such happiness!
Marlow | To Tony. You see now, young gentleman, the effects of your folly. What might be amusement to you, is here disappointment, and even distress.
Tony | From a reverie. Ecod, I have hit it. It’s here. Your hands. Yours and yours, my poor Sulky!—My boots there, ho!—Meet me two hours hence at the bottom of the garden; and if you don’t find Tony Lumpkin a more good-natured fellow than you thought for, I’ll give you leave to take my best horse, and Bet Bouncer into the bargain. Come along. My boots, ho! Exeunt.

Epilogue I

By Dr. Goldsmith

Spoken by Mrs. Buckley in the character of Miss Hardcastle

Well, having stooped to conquer with success,
And gained a husband without aid from dress,
Still, as a barmaid, I could wish it too,
As I have conquered him to conquer you:
And let me say, for all your resolution.
That pretty barmaids have done execution.
Our life is all a play, composed to please;
“We have our exits and our entrances.”
The first act shows the simple country maid,
Harmless and young, of everything afraid;
Blushes when hired, and with unmeaning action,
“I hopes as how to give you satisfaction.”
Her second act displays a livelier scene—
Th’ unblushing barmaid of a country inn,
Who whisks about the house, at market caters.
Talks loud, coquettes the guests, and scolds the waiters.
Next the scene shifts to town, and there she soars,
The chophouse toast of ogling connoisseurs.
On Squires and Cits she there displays her arts,
And on the gridiron broils her lovers’ hearts;
And, as she smiles, her triumphs to complete,
E’en common councilmen forget to eat.
The fourth act shows her wedded to the Squire,
And Madam now begins to hold it higher;
Pretends to taste, at Operas cries caro!
And quits her Nancy Dawson for Che Faro:
Dotes upon dancing, and in all her pride.
Swims round the room, the Heinel of Cheapside;
Ogles and leers, with artificial skill,
Till, having lost in age the power to kill.
She sits all night at cards, and ogles at spadille.
Such, through our lives, th’ eventful history!
The fifth and last act still remains for me:
The barmaid now for your protection prays,
Turns female barrister, and pleads for Bayes.